A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate, Series L FA321
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate, Series L
1879-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, John D. 3rd (John Davison), 1906-1978
FA321
14.82 Cubic Feet 39 document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Scope and Contents note
The Real Estate Interests series deals primarily with the activities of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in New York City and Cleveland.
The material includes routine papers and correspondence for the purchase, maintenance, and sale of property. Purchases of land for gifts to the Rockefeller Institute, Memorial Sloan-Kettering, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, and parks, including Fort Tryon, are documented here.
There are 44 boxes ranging from 1879 to 1961. Most of the material is dated before 1945. The series includes correspondence of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, and Thomas M. Debevoise. There is a small amount of material concerning John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Winthrop Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller.
General note
When this series was processed, the following folders were not found:
Cleveland Property - Rockefeller Building - Sale to Superior-6th Street, 1919-1923 Midtown Development and Investment Corporation - Certificate of Incorporation New York Property - 20 West 53rd Street, 1944-1953 New York Property - West 54th Street, West 53rd Street Properties, 1929-1959 New York Property - 4 West 54th Street, 1924-1938
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Performing arts; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Prohibition; Public health; Public health administration; Public policy; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Public welfare; Religion; Travel; United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Philanthropy; Folk art; Government policy; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; World War II; World War I; Urban renewal; Urban policy; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; International relations; International education; International economic relations; International cooperation; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Medical research; Philanthropy -- United States; Medical education; Medical care; Maternal health services; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Economic development; Art; Economics; Economic policy; Education -- United States; Education; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Business enterprises, Foreign; Capital investments; Arts; Business
- Abeyton Realty Company and Corporation
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Agreements Power of Attorney, 1909-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Power of attorney from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Boulware, Bertram Cutler and Charles O. Heydt to collect mortgages and other obligations; receipts from sales of property; agreement to sell property to company. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, S. H. Holding, A. L. Boulware, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Dissolution [Cleveland Property], 1917-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Certificate of Retirement from State of Ohio; certificate of dissolution. Conveyance of property from Abeyton Realty Company to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, C. E. Terrill, C. A. Hand, Starr J. Murphy, Thomas M. Debevoise, Phillip Keebler.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Incorporation, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Certificate of incorporation; appointment of Terrill as manager and agent in Ohio. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Transfer of Property, 1906-1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Deeds to properties; list and valuation of each parcel transferred. Correspondents include E. V. Cary, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Sale of Property, 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Authorizations to sell property; offers to purchase; valuations and assessments. No offers accepted. Charles O. Heydt's history of Cleveland investments. Correspondents include A. B. Smythe, C. E. Terrill, Harry D. Sims, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - New York State Taxes, 1909-1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Capital stock reports; valuations of properties held. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Federal Taxes; Annual Reports, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Summaries of sales; receipts and taxes paid.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Federal Taxes; Annual Reports - Claim for Refund, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Filing of capital stock returns; claim for refund.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Federal Taxes; Annual Reports - Fiduciaries Return of Net Income (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Filing of returns by fiduciaries and return of payment of salary and commissions to Clarence Terrill.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - United States Income Tax, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Statements of assets and liabilities; valuation of property, sales, rentals collected; taxes paid. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - United States Income Tax - Correspondence, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Sending of income tax returns allowance of claim for abatement of tax.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Terrill Salary, Commissions, 1907-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Instructions to oversee all John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s real estate property in Cleveland, to sell property. Salary and commission arrangements; appointment as personal representative of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. instead of manager of Abeyton Realty Company, when corporation dissolved. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Clarence E. Terrill, L. M. Bowers, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Terrill Suit, Legal Papers, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Claim for broker's commission; legal precedents. Revocation of power of attorney; depositions and related material. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel.
  - Abeyton Realty Company - Treasurer's Report, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Reports of receipts and disbursements; balance sheets. Book values of property; commissions paid.
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation, 1922-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Organization of corporation to hold title to real estate; certificate of incorporation, by-laws; dissolution of corporation. Transfer of property to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; appraisal of property, book value. Correspondents include A. L. Boulware, Bertram Cutler, Robert W. Gumbel, Raymond B. Fosdick, Charles O. Heydt, Phillip Keebler, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    File Plan note
    186
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Balance Sheets, 1924-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Also profit and loss statements.
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Appraisal of Property, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Appraisal of property owned by Abeyton Realty Corporation in 1933 and 1939. Correspondents include Carl A. Palmer, James C. Jones, John Dr. Rockefeller, Jr.
    186.1
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Buffalo Property, 1889-1920 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Purchase of half interest in property; appraisal, assessed value. Offers to purchase property; deed of property to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Transfer of title to Abeyton Realty Company and transfer back to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Sale of property. Correspondents include E. V. Cary, Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., G. D. Rogers, C. E. Terrill.
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Buffalo Property, 1889-1920 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - West 54th Street Properties, 1909-1913 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Deed to property from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Transfer title to Abeyton Realty Corporation; sale to 45th Street Realty Company. Insurance. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. Craige Severance.
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Toledo Property, 1892-1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Payment of taxes; sale of pieces of property; fire; survey of property; partition of property, Rose heirs getting northern half, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. the southern half. Deeding of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. half to Abeyton Realty Company; transfer of property back to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Sale of property to Southern Wheel Company; defects in deed. Sale of property to Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railroad Company. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, Clarence Terrill, H. P. Rose, W. K. Rose, L. C. James.
  - Abeyton Realty Corporation - Toledo Property, 1892-1937 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Cleveland Property
  - Cleveland Property - City Homestead, 1879-1940 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Discontinuance of use of homestead property by Rockefeller family; lease to various companies; transfer to Lawida Corporation. Razing of house. Use of stables as restaurant. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, C. E. Terrill, L. M. Bowers, H. D. Sims.
  - Cleveland Property - Cleveland Boulevard, 1895-1897 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Property purchases and appraisals, improvements. Resolutions from City of Cleveland thanking John D. Rockefeller, Sr. for gifts of land and money for park purposes; letters of appreciation. Construction of arch for parkway. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., George D. Rogers.
  - Cleveland Property - Cleveland Boulevard, 1898-1904 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Survey for Encroachments, 1931-1935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Purchase offers; school board desire to use portion of Ambler Park; study of conveyances of park lands and encroachments on park lands. Cleveland Transit System use of property, with John D. Rockefeller, Sr. consent but desire than principal of non-encroachment be adhered to. Correspondents include Joseph Schlitz, Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Deed to Catholic Diocese, 1928-1935 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Unlawful grant by city for use of park lands by Diocese; payment by city.
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Regarding Deeds to New York Central and City of Cleveland, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Case School Campus - Mount Sinai Hospital, 1938-1957; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Case School Campus - Mount Sinai Hospital, 1938-1957; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Cleveland Property - Boulevard and Park - Assignment of Interests to Rockefeller Brothers Fund, Inc., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Cleveland Property - East Ohio Gas Company, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Decision that construction of gas main through Park not contrary to original gift; permission granted; installation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise, Joseph Schlitz.
  - Cleveland Property - Euclid Avenue and Superior Road, 1899-1931 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Purchase from Green and Schoonmaker; conveyance to Abeyton Realty Company. Reconveyance to city; purchase of parcel by Freeman and Gutentag. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, Charles O. Heydt, N. A. Quilling.
  - Cleveland Property - B. R. Deming - Euclid Golf Allotment, 1909-1913; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Conveyance of right of way to Cleveland Electric Railroad Company; deeds to property from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; appraisal, purchase offers, development possibilities, negotiations, purchase. Appointment as agent for development and sale of property. Improvements to property. Statement of Deming's account; power of attorney to Charles O. Heydt and Starr J. Murphy; sales of property; deeds; releases of mortgages; payment of taxes. Correspondents include C. E. Terrill, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, H. D. Sims, E. V. Cary, A. L. Boulware, Joseph Schlitz.
  - Cleveland Property - B. R. Deming - Euclid Golf Allotment, 1913-1939; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Cleveland Property - Euclid Golf Allotment - Maps, Blueprints, 1914-1916 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Maps, plats and blueprints of Allotment and Shaker Heights.
  - Cleveland Property - Foster Property, 1894-1925 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. leased property to Saginaw Bay Company; then deeded to Abeyton Realty Company; attempts to sell; purchase by Cleveland Terminal Building Company. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Harry D. Sims, Joseph Schlitz.
  - Cleveland Property - Gallup Tract - Maps, Surveys, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Plats of property; Terrill wants to sell tract; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. notes on suggestion that he place real estate into a company to avoid personal relations with the purchasers. Correspondents include Clarence E. Terrill, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Cleveland Property - Gallup Tract - Miscellaneous, 1907-1923 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Sale of property; appraisals. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, S. H. Holding, C. E. Terrill, J. G. W. Cowles.
  - Cleveland Property - Gallup Tract - Miscellaneous - Klier Property, Lot 140, 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Sale of property.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, 246 Lots, 1910-1921; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Sales of property; payment of note. Correspondents include C. E. Terrill, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, Louis H. Wolfe.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, 246 Lots, 1922-1930; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Payment of Wolfe-Sill mortgage; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchase of property. Correspondents include L. H. Wolfe, Charles O. Heydt, Joseph Schlitz, James C. Jones.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Farm - Lots 195-196 - Rockefeller Andrews Allotment, 1912-1921 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Sale of property; signing of quitclaim deed. Correspondents include Joseph Schlitz, S. H. Holding, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Farm Searchers, 1907-1910 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Sales of property; survey; construction of sidewalk. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, C. E. Terrill, H. D. Sims, E. V. Cary.
  - Cleveland Property - Gilbert Property, 1909-1913 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    Maps and correspondence. Used in Terrill suit. Offers to purchase; authorization to sell; sale of parcel to Bratenahl Land Company. Correspondents include C. E. Terrill, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, National City Building Company, 1893-1935 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Valuation of property; assignment of lease from Garfield to Cleveland Building Company; deed of property from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; transfer to Lawida Corporation. Correspondents include L. H. Severance, H. A. Garfield, G. D. Rogers, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Charles O. Heydt, Robert W. Gumbel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, National City Building Company - Euclid Avenue and Bond Street Property, 1892-1894 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    Lease to Garfield and Garfield.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, 246 Lots, 1909-1917; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    Releases of lots under Wolfe's mortgage.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, 246 Lots - Schedules of Release, Price of Lots, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    Lists of lots and valuations.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property, 246 Lots, 1918-1919; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property - Turner and Warner Road Lots, 1914-1943 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Sale of property; sending of deeds. Correspondents include C. A. Hand, C. E. Terrill, L. H. Wolfe, J. Schlitz, J. C. Jones, F. S. Staley.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property - Turner and Warner Road Lots - Ida and Gladys Bartel, Lots 238-239, 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    Sale of property, sending of deed.
  - Cleveland Property - Garfield Property - Maps, Blueprints, Miscellaneous, 1901-1910 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    Sale of property; appraisals; reduction of width of Turney Road; installation of water main. Correspondents include J. G. W. Cowles, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. D. Sims, C. E. Terrill.
  - Cleveland Property - Histories, 1909-1935 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Acquisition of various properties; transfers of deeds. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt.
  - Cleveland Property - Holden Property, 1907-1912 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    Offers to purchase; sales of property. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Clarence Terrill.
  - Cleveland Property - Maps, 1901-1941; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    Map of proposed belt line in Cleveland; Park School property map. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, Frank Staley.
  - Cleveland Property - Maps, 1909-1941; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Cleveland Property - Miscellaneous Letters, 1905-1942 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    Deeds from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Abeyton Realty Company; sales of property; inquiry about The Weddell House by Historic American Building Survey. John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, Robert W. Gumbel, E. V. Cary, Frank Staley.